<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<rfc
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      category="std"
      consensus="true"
      docName="draft-normington-jsonpath-latest"
      ipr="trust200902"
      obsoletes=""
      updates=""
      submissionType="IETF"
      xml:lang="en"
      tocInclude="true"
      tocDepth="4"
      symRefs="true"
      sortRefs="true"
      version="3">
  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 2.38.1 -->
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
    ipr values: trust200902, noModificationTrust200902, noDerivativesTrust200902,
       or pre5378Trust200902
    you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
    they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

 <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

 <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
        full title is longer than 39 characters -->

   <title>JavaScript Object Notation (JSON) Path</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-normington-jsonpath-00"/>
    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

   <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

    <author fullname="Glyn Normington" initials="G" role="editor" surname="Normington">
      <organization>VMware, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city>Winchester</city>
          <region/>
          <code/>
          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>
        <phone/>
        <email>glyn.normington@gmail.com</email>
     </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2020"/>
    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill 
        in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill 
	 in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is 
	 necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the 
	 purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to 
	 specify just the year. -->

   <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

   <area>General</area>
    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>
    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
        IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
        which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

   <keyword>JSON</keyword>
   <keyword>JSONPath</keyword>
    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
        files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
        output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
        keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

   <abstract>
      <t>JSONPath defines a string syntax for identifying values
   within a JavaScript Object Notation (JSON) document.</t>
    </abstract>
    <note>
      <t><strong>This document is a work in progress and has not yet been published as an Internet Draft.</strong></t>
    </note>
  </front>

   <!-- ***** MIDDLE MATTER ***** -->

  <middle>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <!-- move the following to an Acknowledgements appendix and write a proper introduction -->
      <t>JSONPath was introduced by Stefan Goessner as a simple form of XPath for JSON.
         See his original article <xref target="Goessner" format="default">Goessner</xref>.
      </t>
      <t>JSON is defined by <xref target="RFC8259" format="default">RFC&nbsp;8259</xref>.
      </t>

      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Requirements Language</name>
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
       "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
       document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119" format="default">RFC&nbsp;2119</xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>ABNF Syntax</name>
        <t>The syntax in this document conforms to ABNF as defined by <xref target="RFC5234" format="default">RFC&nbsp;5234</xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
   <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>JSONPath Syntax and Semantics</name>
         <section numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Overview</name>
            <t>A JSONPath is a string which matches zero or more nodes of any JSON document. A valid JSONPath conforms to the ABNF syntax defined by this document.
            </t>
         </section>
         <section numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Terminology</name>
            <t>A JSON document is logically a tree of nodes with the document as the root node of the tree.
            </t>
            <t>Each node holds a JSON value (as defined by <xref target="RFC8259" format="default">RFC&nbsp;8259</xref>) of one of the types object, array, number, string, or one
               of the literals <tt>true</tt>, <tt>false</tt>, or <tt>null</tt>. The type of the JSON value held by a node is sometimes referred to as the type of the node.
            </t>
            <t>The descendants of a node are taken to include the node itself and the descendants of any children of the node.
            </t>
         </section>
         <section numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Implementation</name>
            <t>An implementation of this specification, from now on referred to simply as "an implementation", SHOULD takes two inputs, a JSONPath and a JSON document, and produce
               a possibly empty list of nodes of the JSON document which match the JSONPath or an error (but not both).
            </t>
            <t>If there is no matching node and no error has occurred, an implementation MUST return an empty list of nodes.
            </t>
            <t>Syntax errors in the JSONPath SHOULD be detected before matching is attempted since they do not depend on the JSON document.
               Therefore, an implementation SHOULD take a JSONPath and produce an optional syntax error and then,
               if and only if an error was not produced, SHOULD take a JSON document and produce a list of matches or an error (but not both).
            </t>
            <t>Alternatively, an implementation MAY take a JSONPath and a JSON document and produce a list of matches or an optional error (but not both).
            </t>
            <t>For any implementation, if a syntactically invalid JSONPath is provided, the implementation MUST return an error.
            </t>
            <t>If a syntactially invalid JSON document is provided, any implementation SHOULD return an error.
            </t>
         </section>
         <section numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Syntax</name>
            <t>Syntactically, a JSONPath consists of a root selector (<tt>$</tt>), which selects the root node of a JSON document, followed by a possibly empty sequence of <em>matchers</em>.
            </t>
            <sourcecode type="abnf">
json-path = root-selector *matcher
root-selector = %x24               ; $ selects document root node
            </sourcecode>
            <t>The syntax and semantics of each matcher is defined below.
            </t>
         </section>
         <section numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Semantics</name>
            <t>The root selector <tt>$</tt> not only selects the root node of the input document, but it produces as output a list consisting of one node: the input document.
            </t>
            <t>After the root selector, the remainder of the JSONPath passes lists of nodes from one matcher to the next ending up with a list of nodes which is the result of
               matching the JSONPath to the input JSON document.
            </t>
            <t>Each matcher acts on its input list of nodes as follows. For each node in the list, the matcher matches zero or more descendants of the node.
               The output list of nodes of a matcher is the concatenation of the lists of matching descendents for each input node. 
            </t>
            <t>A specific, non-normative example will make this clearer. Suppose the input document is: <tt>{"a":[{"b":0},{"b":1},{"b":2}]}</tt>. As we will see later, the JSONPath
               <tt>$.a[*].b</tt> produces the following list of matching nodes: <tt>0</tt>, <tt>1</tt>, <tt>2</tt>. Let's walk through this in detail.
            </t>
            <t>The JSONPath consists of <tt>$</tt> followed by three matchers: <tt>.a</tt>, <tt>[*]</tt>, and <tt>.b</tt>.
            </t>
            <t>Firstly, <tt>$</tt> matches the input document and produces a list of one node: the input document.
            </t>
            <t>Next, <tt>.a</tt> matches any values of input nodes (which are objects) corresponding to the key <tt>"a"</tt>.
               The result is again a list of one node: <tt>[{"b":0},{"b":1},{"b":2}]</tt>.
            </t>
            <t>Next, <tt>[*]</tt> matches all the elements of input nodes which are arrays.
               The result is a list of three nodes: <tt>{"b":0}</tt>, <tt>{"b":1}</tt>, and <tt>{"b":2}</tt>. 
            </t>
            <t>Finally, <tt>.b</tt> matches any values of input nodes (which are objects) corresponding to the key <tt>"b"</tt>.
               The result is the concatenation of three lists each of length one containing <tt>0</tt>, <tt>1</tt>, <tt>2</tt>, respectively.
            </t>
            <t>As a consequence of this approach, if any of the matchers matches no nodes, then the whole JSONPath matches no nodes.
            </t>
            <t>In what follows, the semantics of each matcher are defined for each type of node.
            </t>
         </section>       
   </section>
   <section anchor="IANA" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>
      <t>All drafts are required to have an IANA considerations section (see
     <xref target="RFC5226" format="default">Guidelines for Writing an IANA Considerations Section in RFCs</xref> for a guide). If the draft does not require IANA to do
     anything, the section contains an explicit statement that this is the
     case (as above). If there are no requirements for IANA, the section will
     be removed during conversion into an RFC by the RFC Editor.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Security" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>This section gives security considerations, as required by <xref target="RFC3552" format="default">RFC&nbsp;3552</xref>.</t>
    </section>
   <section anchor="Alternatives" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Alternatives</name>
      <t>An analogous standard, JSON Pointer, is provided by <xref target="RFC6901" format="default">RFC&nbsp;6901</xref>.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

 <back>
   <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5234.xml"?>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3552.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5226.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6901.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8259.xml"?>
        <reference anchor="Goessner" target="https://goessner.net/articles/JsonPath/">
          <front>
            <title>JSONPath - XPath for JSON</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Stefan Gössner</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2007" month="February"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
      </references>
    </references>
 </back>
</rfc>
